hello I'm your host David Bernard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
biding Our Guest today is Anton derka
co-founder and CEO of sweatcoin one of
the largest health and fitness apps in
the world the past 3 years with more
than 180 million registered users on the
podcast we talk with Anton about
building sustainable viral growth Loops
at scale how to effectively gamify user
incentives and why emotional connections
Thrive more value than purely economic
ones hey Anton thanks so much for
joining us on the podcast today yeah
thank you very much for having me
pleasure and Jacob nice to have you on
as well excited to be here so Anon I
want to kick things off with a little
bit about sweatcoin I don't think our
audience will be as familiar with
sweatcoin as they are with some other
apps especially because you're just now
starting to layer subscriptions on so
it's not kind of well known in the kind
of subscription app industry but I think
you have a lot of interesting things
we're going to be will talk about today
but why don't you just kick it off tell
us a little bit about sweatcoin how it
was founded and what the app is yeah
thank you so so sweatcoin has a very
simple concept um at a score we are
great Believers that physical activity
is valuable and we wanted to create
something that would help people develop
a very healthy habit of continuously
moving we all know that it's very very
hard to be active you know we all have
been on the receiving end of that you
know early January Blue Monday type of
depression you buy a gym membership you
give up you install a new app and you
promise yourself that it's going to work
out like three times a week and then you
before you know it you forgotten about
it so I mean we all know this right you
know building a a habit is difficult why
is it so and you know the funny thing
and that's one of the things that we
kind of discovered very early on is uh
actually we are not born to be active we
are born to be lazy n Mother Nature did
not ever think that we will have excess
calories at some point in time so
actually did not buil in any kind of
Behavioral mechanisms that would
encourage you to be active you know
which is very different to some other
behaviors like take Pro procreation you
know we have orgasm so we procreate
right so I mean easy but well as it
turns out we don't have orgasm for
exercise and we almost kind of you know
obviously the whole thing I'm just
making a bit of a joke but we I was
really kind of fascinated you know I've
been in the sports fitness space for
many years and one of the things that I
was constantly fascinated by is that you
know why you know motivations are not
there for some people and they are for
some others so obviously that the
biggest and the best thing about this is
intrinsic motivation and many of us
actually don't have a problem with that
and we are really lucky truth is that
the about 70% of the world population do
not have that ability and they need to
be approached because you know all of
the fitness industry is based on that
pretty much that very healthy concept of
yeah you get you need to get more
responsible you need to get moving and
everything and that's why you know
there's so much success you look around
yourself everybody is doing something
everybody's going for a walk to the gym
and stuff but the reality is 70% of the
roal population do not buy into this so
we wanted to come up with something
different we wanted to come up with
something less intrusive not like
guild-based or whatever guilt Tri trip
based type of things you know lazy bum
stand up do a 5K and all kind of jazz
and you know obviously loyalty programs
had been around for ages they're popular
and the initial idea was can we actually
come up with some sort of program Air
Miles full steps and this is where it
all started but that's kind of fty
programs are not cool you know you look
at the air miles they're pay and then
you know so obviously we started I
started iterating trying to come up with
a a different level of user engagement
that could actually make people adopt a
new habit and then as I said you know my
initial claim is that physical activity
is valuable and the idea was that very
simply that you know physical activity
is valuable literally because people are
more physically active they are more
productive they are healthier they
destroy less value for the economy
generally because they get ill less
frequently and if we were able to
capture that value One Way or Another
and somehow tokenize it and share it
back with the user would create a an
ongoing flywheel and that's exactly what
we did so yes that's a long story you
know it's story kind of materialized
initially in a form of a loyalty program
then I started chatting to a few friends
I think that I ended up with speaking to
my now co-founder who was like oh man
let's just take it all the way let's
call it a coin and we of course we were
inspired by Bitcoin then it was back in
2015 Bitcoin was still in its infancy
relative infancy so we came up with this
concept of creating like a uh a virtual
kind of point system or token system
next thing we knew is that it just
exploded that whole idea is super
fascinating you know a lot of people
these days are trying to recreate
dualingo the dualingo for this they the
dualingo for that
and you know streaks is kind of an
interesting way to do that but this
whole idea of like this loyalty program
of a coin is an interesting kind of spin
in the other direction of incentivizing
those things so how does sweatcoin
actually work and funny enough I was
telling my wife last night that I was
interviewing the CEO of sweatcoin she's
like sweatcoin that sounds kind of gross
then I was like yes but it's also really
cool it's like you earn coins I didn't
think that for a second for sweating
which is I think a really cool idea so
so how does that actually work and maybe
it' be interesting even to talk through
some early iterations on like what did
work and what didn't work the question I
was going to ask is like how did you
bootstrap that fly you know you talk
about like exercise or sweat being
inherently valuable right but actually
create there needs to be some Arbitrage
there that to actually like capture and
and sort of tokenize that so like how
did you go about bootstrapping the value
for the customer and then also for the
partners yeah brilliant question like a
set of questions so let me ask them one
by one so I think firstly on the name
our original working title was fitcoin
and then we thought it wasn't like it
was too cozy almost like meaningless we
needed something a bit more polarizing
and lots of people especially in the
early days right now it's become a
little bit of a like you know lots of
people have heard about it and they
don't have an issue like here in the UK
we have this brand called Sweaty Betty
and you know it's become such a such a
kind of High Street phenomenon that
nobody thinks about sweaty betties
everybody swey that's it that's fine
it's similar with sweatcoin now I I love
the name just to be clear like what was
cool last night in the conversation with
my wife was that it was polarizing and
it like it led to a conversation like I
said sweat coin she said oo that's gross
or weird and then we had a whole
conversation about like sweating and
like earning for sweat and stuff like
that so I think it was ultimately like a
a really successful name in that way we
love it too yeah so but you know the the
original kind of the starting that you
know the the app is very simple you walk
we make sure that those steps are real
so we run a piece of software that we
call a valid dator actually ensures that
you know you cannot put it on a dog as
some people suggest on top of a washing
machine or create a farm in Vietnam and
you know like uh fake the system and
then you know every Thousand Steps give
you a sweat coin and then you can turn
those sweat coins into you know product
Services experiences donate to charity
and you know send to your friends so
that's a very simplistic type of
activity now now coming back to your
original question about gamification now
look gamification has been around for
ages I think the first time I kind of
consciously heard about it I think was
back in I would to say maybe 2005 when I
had a course from corsera called
gamification and all that kind of jazz
the streaks the badges leaderboards it
was all there so you know the human you
know the humankind has known about
gamification for ages you know but it's
just easier said than done so I think Jo
lingo did really really well what they
do is a different toolkit you know they
do gamification really really well and
we went slightly down down a slightly
different route which is incentives the
use of incentives because you know one
thing that Fitness kind of lacks a
little bit is that all the fitness apps
they're kind of similar you are being
requested to kind of do something that's
generally unnatural you don't you don't
want to especially for those people who
are not Fitness junkies but you know
yeah just do something and and that's it
you know we wanted to take a slightly
different angle and kind of make it fun
essentially the promise there is that
look you know you walk anyway why don't
you try and earn something useful so
it's a very different concept very
different message when we just launched
we intentionally the product concept was
that we didn't want to look like a
fitness app so the look and feel was
much more of a financial app where you
had the kind of the bullet and you'd had
a
Marketplace and the techy very techy
look you know we had a very cool kind of
generator Graphics there it was cold and
was a bit we definitely pay some
tributes to the kind of the emerging
crypto scene there because we wanted to
kind of you know to to congratulate the
new movement and stuff like that so all
of that essentially we became the only
financially looking up in in health and
fitness so I think that created a lot of
Buzz that was really really interesting
again don't forget that we launch the
app in 2016 it was very early days of
crypto and some people would just you
know have no idea idea and then I think
our first stage of growth obviously
timing lucky as many products are we
launched in the Ico boom of 2017 but I
think what was really really important
there as well you know you know we
launched and then you know the press the
media picked up on the story because it
was fun lots of people wrote about us we
got our first initial whatever 30 40,000
users which was great amazing but then
obviously we hit a bit of a wool in
terms of how do you continue to grow and
you know funny I remember we apped to Y
combinat we made it to the very final
round and then we got rejected and they
said guys you need to grow faster
because we were so happy and we were so
proud that our retention was Skyrocket
you know rocketing in terms of other
Health and Fitness Products because
health and fitness is really difficult
to retain users and we were doing so
well on our first kind of 50,000 user
base so we thought that was good enough
but they said no that's not good enough
you guys need to figure out growth so we
came back to the grow the drawing board
that was November I want to say November
and we said look you know we need to get
to like 300 users every day and then we
came up with this idea to actually turn
things around we just realized that
unlike other apps or products that
actually if you want to build a referral
program you all of a sudden you need to
have quite a lot of cash to be able to
fund it now we didn't have to do it
because we had our own currency we were
our own Central Bank so to speak so we
created a usage Jour a very simplistic
one so if you B into this idea you
install the app you know you see a a
very simplistic today's screen there's
two things you can do to earn sweat
coins you can either start walking or
you invite a friend for five sweat coins
and that created quite a lot of that
intrinsic virality where we made the
earning sweat coins essentially earning
sweat coins is the user experience of
course as in any kind of gaming e
economics you need to provide ways for
people to do something with El coin once
they've been earned but you know that
that happens usually later and this is
how we solve the call start problem so
uh we created that inherent Loop that's
ingrained into the core user experience
I think this is what's so special about
our gross engine and that kind of helped
us to get over the line and we got to
300 users a day and then a th and then
5,000 and then as I said you know
gradually that you know the train
gathered speed and we ended up just uh
raising around in about N9 months later
from Goodwood capsu finally enough one
of my interns about 9 months later in
the summer of 2017 he said do you guys
mind if I reapply to Y combinator I said
I don't think it's needed but hey why
don't you go ahead do it so he did and
we ended up being accepted by that time
we already kind of signed a term sheet I
really wanted to get into by combinat
but on our on our terms that wasn't
acceptable for them so we kind of passed
on them so it's a funny one things
changed in 12 months a lot so uh no but
I think that you know credit to them I
think the conversation was really useful
just a point of clarification so from
the beginning this like sweat coin it's
a is it a literal crypto coin like is it
on a chain no it's like a virtual
currency essentially that the moment
will launched there was only two
blockchains out there the first one is
Bitcoin right ethereum was like just
starting ethereum was just a startup
with metalic and went for a walk down
down the river THS the South Bank he
walks very very fast by the way but we
concluded there that you know we were
not not in a position to build our own
blockchain no need yeah I mean I think
it would have been then obviously the
user experience challenges were crazy
they still are it was slow it was
expensive it was like everything like so
it was only in 22 when the technology
was of age and we were ready to
essentially partnering with sweat
Foundation to launch a crypto
proposition which is a separate thing to
sweat coins there's no connection but we
are partnering the organization and some
of our users who actually decide to op
in they can convert their steps into a
sweat token but that's a separate story
sweatcoin continues to be a health and
fitness app it's disconnected from sweat
Foundation but it's essentially the fiat
currency right with the app of sweatcoin
right you control well technically
speaking it's a it's an inapp currency
you know and then our job is just to
make sure that it's useful for our users
to make that sweatcoin you know to earn
that sweatcoin because they find it
useful I wanted to dig into that idea of
the sweatcoin being valuable to users it
just dawned on me while you were talking
that I created a form of sweatcoin for
my son he's like 16 super into Ai and
computers and he'd rather just spend all
day on his computer and so just this
weekend I made his allowance contingent
upon getting certain physical extra shot
I created my own sweatcoin I should just
you know get them on the sweatcoin App
instead but for him now there is direct
like monetary value to him doing
exercise and that's a that's highly
incentivized for him how did you early
on and then how has it evolved in making
the sweatcoin actually valuable and
something that people actually want and
are incentivized to get so look you know
let me rephrase the question again so
lots of people basically question okay
how is that possible where does the
value come from and when we just started
so obviously we researched the graveyard
of other companies that Tred to do
something similar and what they failed
you know the most obvious answer there
is that okay I need to find a backer you
know I need to find somebody who
provides the value because in your in
your example you are the backer of the
whatever that kind of the value that you
that your son is creating by by being
active and the most obvious answers are
one of the three it's either a health
care provider it's a healthare insurer
it's a health insurer or it's an
employer all those stakeholders are
potentially interested in you being
active the approach with that you know
it wasn't and we were not excited about
you know any of the three as you know I
mean when you start up trying to
penetrate the Healthcare System unless
you've got some incredible
competitive Advantage near impossible
same applies to health insurance and
with employer you know Corporal Wellness
is a is a red ocean it's a very busy
area lot of competition you know the
check size is small Revenue retention is
low it's hard to compete so we kind of
went back to the drawing board we said
we need to find something different and
we kind of concluded that our best shot
really is to create such a sticky user
experience that users would love the
experience and as a result the brands
the partners that we would were hoping
to partner with they'll be able to
provide lots of value in kind to make it
worth their while so I mean the way we
designed the user experience we didn't
want to create an Amazon kind of way you
can exchange your your sweat coins for
like thousands of different products not
because we didn't want to because we
knew we couldn't get all those products
in who would give them to us so we
created a small curated list where there
would be like four products only every
day and there would be a new product
every day so essentially 12 products
weekly and you know we had a good enough
Network to find 12 different brands that
would give us some value in kind because
they love the idea and this is how we
reserve the cold start problem and we
started getting those users and the
number of users gradually started to
increase and then at some point in time
we just realized that some of those
vends as used we used to call them
actually were queuing outside the door
saying oh guys when can you feature us
we are du to be featured next November
can we actually move it forward a couple
of months and this is when we realized
that the number of users and the kind of
the attention span we were generating
the level of Engagement was big enough
for us starting you know to start
monetizing those us and then the other
kind of thing that we did at that stage
we just realized that we were very anti-
ads and I'm still anti- ads because
whenever you think about ads you think
about the bloody banner and that's
something completely irrelevant and then
we discovered that some of our users and
this this practice of rewarded video
some of our users their retention and
engagement improve considerably when we
let them watch a video where they are at
Liberty to decide whether they want to
do it or not so essentially we introduce
a product where you could get one s coin
if you watch the video till the end but
you don't have to do it A and B we would
restrict the number of times that you'd
be able to do it initially it was just
once a day and so then we experimented
to some users actually the the threshold
was three times a day and then if you
try to allow them to watch it more
frequently then the retention drops but
actually one to three times actually
retention and engagement improved it's
completely counterintuitive but you know
the people in the gaming world and then
I obviously I started researching much
more into this people in the mobile
gaming World know this so sometimes
there's a group of users so about 20% of
our users they engage with us they love
it the rest of them hate it and it's
fine these were the early kind of the
things and then so again you know we we
solved the kind of the call start
problem and then we were really lucky to
post through that value of death where
you have too many users to you know have
negligible costs and uh we went on the
other side of the kind of tunnel and
then already kind of we had scale and we
were able to monetize somewhat so you
mentioned in an abstract like partnering
and creating value and kind those
partners are they giving full products
like what is the actual value is it a
discount on gym equipment or the
original idea that I had is that look
you know nobody's going to be excited to
get access to a coupon because you could
go to Groupon and get get a discount
voucher so early version was like yeah
it could be just you know 100% paid in
sweat coin just real product I remember
like we secured a deal with our friends
at VI be food the uh the flat Soul
running shoes very very cool and they
said okay we'll give you 100 pairs of
our last year's collection and we put
them on the on the marketplace and like
you know the users were static but then
obviously as you continue to scale as
you go Global it becomes a bit less kind
of manageable from a complexity
perspective so we do have discount
vouchers but we also make sure that
whatever you can find on sweatcoin is
pretty unique of course it depends very
much on the geography as well so there's
a there's a wide range of different
things and some of the things you can
get only for swep coins like 100% of it
and then you can get some discount
vouchers there's a plenty of different
stuff and so then the value for the
brand like Vivo Barefoot they gave you
the shoes but then essentially it
becomes kind of like an ad for them and
then the hundred people who tens of
thousands of people see Viva Barefoot
and then they go look for oh maybe I
actually just want to purchase this and
then those that get it for free then
then maybe over the next decade they buy
10 more pairs of via barefoot shoes
after getting it for free or will that
happens even more immediately because
you know you have a way of just going
straight into we be food's website and
just you know buy whatever use use
whatever you got because this is how you
do we do fulfillment we don't do
fulfillment ourselves it's done by our
partners and you know from that
perspective you went there bought a pair
of shoes and maybe also bought something
else oh right so there's always that you
know kind of the revenue kind of
generation opportunity any other fun
examples of of partners that you've
worked with this is just so fascinating
to me again like thinking through this
this idea of coins and retention and
gamification that you're like giving
real products to people for exercising
yeah any other like fun examples oh look
I mean obviously in Co everybody was so
excited about digital experiences it was
just like amazing for us because we
didn't like you know one of the
potential kind of difficulties is always
that Redemption process on the
Fulfillment because you know we are in
the game of instant gratification and if
you can only get your product after a
few days that's not instant is it but
when you get a subscription like you
know we worked with whatever Spotify of
Apple music and these guys like you know
the basically the propositions that you
can get the first three months for swe
coins and then the rest of it is paid
through you know Fiat cash and uh that
was just amazing so we really absolutely
loved it but there was like in lots of
lots of people who would like you know
at some point in time in some markets
our positioning was that we are a
product Discovery platform and there
were lots of you know without traffic
lots of new startups doing some really
cool things in the health and wellness
space like you know Innovative kind of
the wearable sensors apparel and stuff
like that and they would just you know
they would always struggle with
distribution because you know you do
when you start from scratch and we would
be that kind of a really really welcome
partner for them because we would be
just showcasing that product to our user
base and the user base was very attuned
and receptive to this and it was just
great yeah that's so fascinating so it's
really interesting to me that the next
layer that you layered on there so you
talked about this referral program where
you give five sweat coins for somebody
who invites a friend but now you have a
whole influencer Hub what does that look
like and how did you layer that on look
I mean one thing leads to another as it
usually happens and you know we kind of
early early stage we just noticed that
there was some users that would bring in
like massive numbers and I'm not talking
about like 10 20 30 invites we're
talking like hundreds sometimes
thousands so obviously we started
digging and we realized that some of our
early users would have a considerable
following on on social media there were
early adopters they loved it and then
they just you know because we provided
that functionality we kind of they were
able to share the link on their profiles
and then lots of users would come in
because everybody loved the idea it was
so fresh and everybody kind of loved it
and people love to share and when we
realized that were people like this we
also realized one really interesting
thing at that stage it was just the
beginning of the influencer movement and
there were like big influences and there
were everybody else and there were some
people that maybe had like 10,000
followers which is not insignificant but
there was no way for them to monetize
I'm not sure how familiar with the
influencer business but if you're an
influencer there's two major things that
really that are really annoying firstly
when you work with a brand usually do
that through an agency unless you're a a
massive influencer and that's a hassle
because the a agency works as a uh kind
of you know as a bridge and they tell
you what to do what not to do so it
takes lots of iterations and speaking
way and then the second thing even if
your contents got you know okayed by the
brand then you know it's very very hard
to see what kind of efficiency you know
whether you drove any results in stalls
and if you did how much and when are you
going to get the money so the money this
the cycle is very very long so what we
realize is that there was a gap that
wasn't essentially covered by anyone of
that midcap so to speak influen and
those guys and you know when we
discovered that we created a special
market place or a special level that
would only open up to user they invited
30 people successful so you just install
the app you start working and then once
that number which we counted inly all of
a sudden you kind of reach more than 30
influencers uh 30 invites then a secret
section of the marketplace opens up and
you can convert your installs into a
bigger better range of prices and we
would have like you know a thousand
invites would buy you a PlayStation and
5,000 invites would buy you a flat
screen TV or something like that just
I'm making up those numbers up but was
the idea and when we did that that b
basically started spreading like
wildfire because lots of people with
anywhere between five and 50,000
followers which is again not massive but
it's not insignificant either they kind
of had a way of essentially turning
their following following into something
very tangible very quickly and that's
something that essentially prompted the
idea of an influencer Hub which is in in
effect this is a like a a separate
version of the app that's available for
the for people who are very rich on
invoice which is a very similar app but
there's an extended functionality
there's extended range of prizes and as
extended service so to speak like think
of it as a VIP version of the app it's
so fascinating have you since then also
layered on any kind of native ad content
or viral content on top of that that you
directly work with influencers or has it
all been through that influencer Hub so
look I mean we start obviously we
started with influencer Hub and you know
we got ourselves in a position where we
we did not do any paid acquisition at
all which is just so incredible I mean
people are going to be listening to this
and just I well I mean I'll challenge
giving away a slat screen TV as a form
of paid acquisition right with more
steps I agree with you yes but then
again I think that that was like that
was probably ENC counted for like 5% of
all our users and it fits into the model
right it's part of the part of the core
Loop anyway it's really interesting it's
really interesting because then at that
stage and that's right now it's been
written about very widely I think
there's like lots of people talk about
it because there's lots of viral
products out there the issue with viral
products is that you can create an
explosion but when it dies down like you
are not in control of things because
virality is uncontrollable it's like
nuclear synthesis it's basically a
nuclear reaction you can have an
explosion but how do you create a
nuclear power station where you can
control the nuclear reaction and that
was the biggest challenge for us because
we could have the that massive Spike
like 30,000 users daily and then it
would just go back to like two or three
I remember then I was talking to one
kind of very very smart data scientist
and you know I said can you build us a
model that would help us understand how
we create a virality and he was a
specialist in stochastic processes
whatever that means and he said look you
know he did it he did some studying and
then he said well one thing I can do the
only thing I can do I can tell you that
the virality or the viral spike is is
inevitable one thing I cannot do I
cannot tell you when and that wasn't
particularly kind of useful because fair
enough you just sit there just waiting
maybe it's going to happen tomorrow
maybe it's going to happen three months
but you don't know so anyway we kind of
started building that sort of approach
now what we did then is we just realized
that there are certain stages in
creating that controlled nuclear
reaction and the first stage is you need
to kickart the process you need to
create what we call a ground swell the
ground swell where you create a little
bit of that noise around the brand so
that people who have some following they
start listening they kind of they know
about the product they've heard about it
because that's important and that is
best done when you do it through the
influencers that you're friendly with
but those influencers need to develop a
Content that's very native to the
channel they use because at the very
early days of Instagram it was very
different you know lots of people would
post content that would be not
necessarily kind of seen as genuine lots
of professionally developed content
early days again we now know that for
example Tik Tok is like famous like you
cannot full users that they will you
know they will spot a fake a mile out so
we started experimenting we started
working with those influencers that we
were friendly with and then when you
kind of you start developing that
content you become really ATT tuned to
what the users need in those channels
and then slowly but surely we've
developed that expertise where we kind
of we were able to work with influencers
then take the content they there was a
winning content they would produce and
we a would share it with other
influencers you help them develop their
own just give them some ideas and some
of them we started using our in our pet
advertising like our pay Debs constitute
right now around about 10% of the total
still only but that's a very important
kind of starting point this is how we
create the ground SWR from the ground
swell with then
accelerated and what's really important
probably the key the truly unique part
of the growth engine is that when you
create the virality then the velocity of
invites drops sharply what that means
what's velocity is the time that is
between one user installing inviting
another one the next user installing
because guess what when the velocity of
invites shrinks you could have six or
seven people or sometimes more in you
know the chain happen happening within
24 hours and when that happens the
algorithm start to pick you up and you
get lots of organic kind of Organics
through app stores and uh and Google and
everything so essentially just creating
that you know this sequence of steps
where you start creating your ground
well where you get the influencers
working with you they develop native
content then it's being picked up
because again I'll use it to use the
virality is very strong the moment you
create that Spike then it's being picked
up the main thing by the user to user
virality and then the Organics kick in
and you become the number one health and
fitness app and sometimes occasionally
the globally you know we were number one
app globally in the US Brazil 65 other
countries have not mistaken so like you
know of course you cannot sustain it but
you can sustain the number one place in
the category for example I mean you
can't sustain any one Spike but like
this is sort of goes back to just App
Store Marketing in general which is like
a you know getting featured or whatever
if you can create a somewhat repeatable
process of knowing oh we we'll generate
so many viral spikes a year that starts
to become like a somewhat of a reliable
Channel that's not easy and you know we
kind of we've fine tuned this girl
engine over the years and right now we
are like literally we we don't we don't
have that many spikes almost at all like
we're very stable yeah but it takes time
it takes experimentation we haven't seen
it there was a period there during 2020
21 where we would see a lot more viral
spikes and apps I don't think we see
that as much David I mean our famous
widget kit is our friend uh a very
famous example went like Mega viral was
that in 2021 2020 something like and
just like nothing I'd ever seen before
in terms of like how fast it went and
yeah it's been a little bit I feel like
more metered since then I don't know
maybe it's more people have rushed into
influencer marketing and stuff like that
it's become a little more competitive
but it's an interesting observation yeah
it's so fascinating building that growth
engine on I love the analogy too of like
controlling a nuclear reaction and then
figuring out how to get that spark and
then how to like keep getting that spark
to like maintain that growth but I think
that you know the next question then is
like okay this is an incredible growth
engine and being able to acquire so many
users at such a relatively cheap cost
compared to a lot of other folks in the
industry is just an incredible leg up
but then how does sweatcoin actually
make money like how do you then monetize
those free users that you've brought in
so Luke I mean as I said the two main uh
monetization channels is the commercial
Partnerships with Brands and then the
kind of the the ads that I described
which we've kind of you know F tune over
the years however it was very very clear
that the advertising model will only
take us that far even the much bigger
user base type of products they kind of
struggle with it a little bit like you
know look at Twitter you know they
decided to Pivot and I think that you
know for us it was essential to be
independent from the health healthare
Partnerships the insurance partnership
the corporate Wellness we know we'll go
there one day but I think there's a far
kind of much lower hanging fruit and
that is subscription because you know
with subscription I think the name of
the game is how cheaply you can acquire
uses at scale because everybody at one
point or another they face the music
they kind of they end up in a situation
where you kind of you know you continue
to grow your C and very very hard we Pro
it probably took us a bit longer because
I think that we probably got a little a
bit too excited about the fact that we
got the profitability at the time when
everybody else was just essentially
crashing a burning like you know we got
the profitability at the very beginning
of covid and I think that I probably
just you know got a little bit over
excited as I said so I think that we
probably took that decision to go a
subscription maybe a year 18 months too
late in retrospect but I think right now
what's totally amazing is that we
launched a very basic subscription we
did a a very kind of very very kind of
low grad type of development and we
already have considerable month Revy so
from that perspective that's a really
important and exciting opportunity there
and then beyond that subscription so of
course you've got that like you know we
worked with the NHS which is the
National Health Service in the UK you
know these guys essentially the number
one spend line for them is diabetes type
two 11% of the total budget of the NHS
goes into diabetes 2 and the NHS
developed what they call the the
national diabetes prevention program
ndpp and that's administered to users
through the kind of private
providers and that ndpp actually works
it's administered to people with
pre-diabetic State and that aims to
essentially drive them away from the
edge of the cliff the problem with the
existing program is that its completion
rate is very low it's about 20 to 25%
which means that the other 75 to 80% of
patients they end up with you know
diabetes 2 with probability close to one
now when sweat coin participates and
plays a role of an engagement platform
for the NHS that completion rate goes
from 25% to 89% this is how we work you
know when with a partner that
essentially provides the extra liquidity
so to speak they provide an extra range
of products that makes the whole
experience for the user even more
exciting because on average a sweatcoin
use it becomes 20% more active using a
free version of the app but let's say in
case of the NHS when they come in and
fund an additional range of prizes and
other incentives that number goes up to
45% and users lose about 6% of their
body weight in 10 weeks and all this
kind of just so the model is there but
the B2B is a very different Beast is the
NHS doing anything to promote actual
like installation I don't want to go
into discussing the how good NHS are in
terms of digital well I don't know are
they handing out QR codes at at doctor's
offices and stuff for you guys or is it
it's but it's purely their funding their
funding no it's it's a little bit more
complex than this it's you know requires
a deeper integration but why I'm saying
in this is that there's unlimited
opportunities in the B2B space but I
think that just generally speaking we
still want to continue to be true to our
roots of the b2c and from that
perspective you know the Spates of
cryption is such a a no-brainer and you
know look you know at this stage we are
running about you know two-thirds of all
our user base is actually free and we on
board anywhere between like 60 and
80,000 users every day it's a massive
scale as is for any health and fitness
product retention is the name of the
game you kind of move retention by 1%
and that's a massive uplift but just
coming back to that pay subscription
conversation look you know there's a
there's lots of opportunity in there and
we've just started with scratching the
surface there's plenty of stuff I think
that the good thing there is that lots
of people as you already kind of
mentioned you know lots of people in the
subscription base space they start with
subs and then they hit a ceiling and
then they try to diversify into other r
streams I think with us with us you know
subscriptions in a funnier way it's a
much more well understood path and lots
of people have done amazing things so
it's relatively easier for us just you
know to take a couple of pages from
their book and uh and continue to build
yeah I'm just looking at the the premium
offering and much more matches like what
you would see like like a Pokemon go or
like some other games that layer on
subscription which is like you get
premium access to stuff that people
don't get it's not necessarily like a
content and feature unlock it's like a
boost to your ability to play the game
which I think fits really well you know
and it kind of becomes a no-brainer if
there somebody who's very serious about
this like to put in a little bit of
money and you'll get a lot of Leverage
out of your usage you think of things
like a family subscription like you know
one of the things that very early days
Michael founder he actually packed his
at the pocket money to his kids to the
number of sweat Co that were genu rating
yeah I gotta do this but so much we can
do because you know at the end of the
day walking is the type of activity
that's available to almost everyone you
know that's that's almost like breathing
and it's such a an endless area of
opportunity and physical activity and
again because of many of my friends who
are in technology sector we are moving
less and less because we're slay to
convenience you know it all started with
the remote control but right now you
don't have to step outside to buy food
anymore you don't have to almost do
anything so before you know it we're all
in w e kind of uh you know we'll move in
those capsules I got to go to Sam's Club
and ride one of the scooters the other
day unrelated but related so I got to
experience it that's scary man I know I
was like oh your point earlier about
there being no natural incentive to you
know I was like if everybody had a
scooter you just would you know uh
Superior for those who have zero
contacts on Twitter Jacob broke his foot
like a month ago and had a massive
surgery and so even more sedentary than
usual you would have to give me a dang
sweat coin I'll go I would love to go
walk 10 miles right now that'd be
amazing but now now I have double reason
so Jacob kind of alluded to it but I
wanted to dig a little deeper into how
you thought about layering value into
the subscription and as you mentioned
even you know you kind of are doing the
reverse of what so many people in the
industry do of like spending a ton on
paid ads putting people right into
subscription a lot of apps are even
doing hard pay walls now you know apps
are switching to hard pay walls then you
hit a ceiling and then then you have to
figure out oh gosh how do we get our
customer acquisition cost down you know
how do we layer on aium products so you
you've kind of done this in the opposite
but I think it'd be really interesting
to hear how you thought about creating
value for users in that subscription
like what's that kind of like primary
motivation for somebody to actually pay
when the premium product is so good look
first of all we've built a product with
inherent limitations like there's only
that type of products that the free
version can afford so to speak there's
you know we would always set a ceiling
on the number of sweat coins you can
earn on a day on a given day so because
of that you know we needed to create a
kind of e economy that would be
sustainable so we introduced a bunch of
restrictions early on that we actually
can lift or remove one of those
restrictions so to speak because you
know we talked a lot about ads and I was
kind of very excited about it but then
let's face it some of the users even
those users that do not engage with
those apps the ads they kind of see the
ad and it's not necessarily the ideal
experience so I think we moving ads to
some users that's a massive value
proposition I'm not saying that's the
only thing we're going to do but
essentially just removing the
restrictions that are inherent to the
free experience I think that's a massive
one but then there's a bunch of other
features that are so to speak more
expensive and cannot be justified for
the free user a case Point like we are
working on a walking coach you know is
someone who essentially helps you with
you know provides the nudges provides
those not necessarily inside no no a
robot of course not a human like you
cannot justify a human really of users
so there's a bunch of different things
that can only be available to a pay
subscription and that arises very
naturally from the user experience
because you know I we always think about
sweatcoin as a platforming experience on
top of which you can build so much more
and like that's like literally we've
built that very platforming use case
where it's very simple you walk your
steps are being converted sweat coin has
been issued and there there's a bunch of
basic things you can do with them that's
all and then you can stop building okay
there's other ways alternative ways to
earn there's alternative ways to spend
there's alternative ways to kind of do
something with that s coin and that all
very nicely feeds into the pay
subscription idea now the way I like
like to think about you know this and I
know it sounds a bit controversial
because most of the market would say
yeah you can start at top and then you
kind of like you you launch a a more
expensive car and then you can create a
mass market car but sometimes you can
like launch a Southwest and then you can
create like a premium experience and the
premium experience will be the same
plane just wider seats better quality
food better service and people would
would be prepared to pay because at the
end of the day like all our users we
divide them broadly into two groups the
ones that come for rewards and the ones
that come for health the ones that come
for rewards they're less sticky but some
Chun a considerable chunk of them they
actually they qualify into what we call
come for rewards state for health they
come for the free stuff and then before
you know it they go like oh man I'm
working 40% more wow that's cool I'm no
long kind of interested yeah I'm pass
rewards but you know what I'm hook up on
working how do you distinguish like what
are the signals you see that tells you
like what category somebody's in based
on behaviors or well I mean we do lots
of user research we observe lots of kind
of user Behavior patterns like those
users who engage with with ads more they
tend to be more rewards focused there
are some users actually it's incredible
how the balance itself serves as a
progression system because you know
essentially what we've done and you know
it's it's it's really amazing we just
reframe steps because you know we used
to have Fitbit and the Fitbit is
wonderful but then you kind of 10,000
steps next morning zero 2,000 steps
afterwards this man it's come on
it's like a it's the same thing again
the moment you reframe and you say these
are not steps these are coins and here's
your balance and your balance keeps on
growing and you're actually quite rich
and I know it's for myself even now I'm
looking at my balance my balance is like
whatever 10 15,000 sweat coins makes me
feel good and bought in like there's
like literal lock in there yeah man I
got make what's a fat I really want to
get to 20,000 I'm rich so I think that
that refraining that's a major that's a
that's a massive that's a very powerful
thing and I think that that's you know
coming back to what we started with it
you know understanding behavioral
economics Behavioral Science generally I
think it's useful yeah I mean I think
there's lessons there for anybody
building an app it doesn't necessarily
have to be direct a coin or an analogy
like that but the more that a users
experience can vary with relation to the
amount of time and effort they've
invested into your app like you'll
create those hooks right and that that
has Downstream effects on retention and
it doesn't even have to be all like
there's no logic there there's really no
there's no literal value but like I
guess literal value is not a thing right
it's all in the eye of the beholder so
if that if if you value having a high
balance it now has value right correct
lots of that because lots of people get
a little bit too literal talking about
the value of sweatcoin and you know we
always like to think and differentiate
the kind of the rational value element
and then the emotional value what's
really interesting is that we we around
this test when we ask users so how much
do you value your sweat coins at oh like
what's the exchange rate how much would
you buy for somebody else's sweat coin
and people then would say anywhere
between one and 5 cents and then we ask
them how much would you sell your sweat
coins from and guess what the answer was
I'm going to guess higher 50 cents to a
dollar which means that basically your
own steps or actually I bet David you
know the steps of your of your son are
going to be far more important to you
then let's say my steps or somebody
else's that you don't even know it's
really interesting considering it's
fully fungible like oh man that's that's
just like a it's Endless Possibilities
there and we're just scratching the
surface there yeah yeah I mean it tells
you you haven't really created a
currency because it has no currency
right it has no bidirectional trade
value the it's got an asymmetry in
bidirectional trade a really interesting
conversation we had a long time ago when
we just started with a dino one of the
top Business Schools and he said like
I'm not sure that you necessarily want
to go crypto because then the magic will
disappear I think actually it's a fair
point because there's this discrepancy
in that the market value versus the
perceived value the yeah yeah you don't
want to you don't want to shatter
anybody's perception right so I think
there there's lots of really interesting
stuff and you know I appreciate that we
kind of we just scratching the surface
here and we're probably not digging
deeper into it just yet I just valued
all my Pokemon cards for when I was a
kid and it and it's destroyed me I wish
i' had never done it in my head it was
worth thousands of dollars and now now
turns out not really held on them for 25
years for nothing in talking through
that it actually reminded me of a
conversation we had with somebody who is
really early at Tinder and how like this
idea of the economics inside of an app
can help fuel the monetization so like
with Tinder and you're talking about how
like certain things are limited within
the app and then you buy the
subscription to kind of like uncap that
and it's similar like with Tinder when
they really exploded with monetization
was when they layered on like you get
one boost a month for the subscription
but then you can buy additional boosts
to get attention and this whole idea of
like creating an economy inside of an
app where and Jacob said it it's like
you you pay to be more effective playing
the game is just such a a fascinating
concept for an app to build this economy
inside the app well I think the gaming
companies are very good at it and
they've been have it for like 10 you
know decades and they are very good
building the experiences where which
which create that scarcity naturally so
I think that you know and uh a good
friend of mine who is uh like a like a a
very successful serial founder in the
gaming space his thesis is that you know
the gaming the mobile gaming hyper
casual casual they know so much about
the user that all that information all
that knowledge should be transferred
into the app world and there so much to
learn for the for us in the in the app
space and that that's happening as we
speak L and you know actually everybody
mentions dingo they doing exactly that
they just using some and let's face it
that's a very basic gameification
mechanics that's been known to the human
current for decades and they just
implementing and just killing it and
doing it really Tastefully too right
they've done very little at the right
amount at the right time and they've
maintained a brand alongside of it which
I think is is rare yeah I think probably
some amount of nose turning in the app
world to some of the techniques that are
used in hyper casual because yeah
because some of it's not all not all
that great but at the core of it like
there's a lot of stuff there that if you
if you bring over appropriately you can
really supercharge so one thing I want
to say about gamification some people
want to stick it pretty much into every
hole the reality is that in order for
gamification to work well there's got to
be an underlying experience that's
actually good for the people and they
know it if the gamification is used for
you to watch more ads you may be
successful shortterm but long term it's
not going to work I think why dingo is
so successful they layer that
gamification on top of the fundamentally
good thing which is learning a language
you know for us it's being more active
and that's why people kind of they agree
to be slightly manipulated because
people are not stupid I mean they
understand that this streak is yeah it's
but they they play the game they play
the ball so I think that's that's my
view on gamification I think
gamification can be super successful if
applied properly to the right underlying
experience yeah I love it you know you
guys are are pushing being more active
do lingo is pushing learning I think
that's a great place to wrap up but as
we wrap up anything else you want to
share I'm going to link to I know y are
actually hiring for a lot of roles right
now but anything else you want to share
as we're wrapping up no I think that you
know it's exciting times for us in the
space of uh Behavior change I think it's
really really exciting that there are
some successful products there I'm
really excited about the right mix of
incentives and gamification and building
a long-term sticky product and then of
course you know uh subscriptions is an
area that we are doubling down on right
now and uh would be great to catch up
with you guys again in another six to n
months maybe and see how we're
progressing absolutely thank you so much
for joining us this is such a fun
conversation thank you very much guys
David Jacob everyone Thanks a all for
having
me thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community